Guide to the Daniel Rubin Papers TAM.657
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Communist Party National Organizational Bureau and Department, 1930-1991; 47 Linear Feet in 74 manuscript boxes, 9 record cartons, 1 half manuscript box and 6 cassette boxes; 145 audiocassettes
  - Subseries I.C: Conventions, 1955-1991; 7.5 Linear Feet in 15 manuscript boxes and 1 record carton
    - Convention, 19th: Memos, 1969 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Convention, 20th: Administrative, 1972 (Box 243, Folder 1-2)
    - Convention, 20th: Constitution, 1972 (Box 243, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 20th: Guests and Staff, 1972 (Box 243, Folder 4)
    - Convention, 20th: Notes and Resolutions, 1972 (Box 243, Folder 5)
    - Convention, 20th: Pre-Convention Discussion, 1971-1972 (Box 243, Folder 6-9)
    - Convention, 20th: Reports and Agendas, 1972 (Box 243, Folder 10-11)
    - Convention, 20th: Reports and Resolutions, 1972 (Box 244, Folder 1-6)
    - Convention, 20th: Slogans, 1972 (Box 244, Folder 7)
    - Convention, 21st: Administrative, 1975 (Box 244, Folder 8)
    - Convention, 21st: Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 244, Folder 9)
    - Convention, 21st: Draft Resolutions, 1975 (Box 244, Folder 10-11)
    - Convention, 21st: Main Political Resolution, 1974 (Box 239, Folder 7, Box 245, Folder 1-2)
    - Convention, 21st: Notes, 1976 (Box 50, Folder 7, Box 245, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 22nd: Agendas and Procedures, 1979 (Box 245, Folder 4-5)
    - Convention, 22nd: Commission, 1979 (Box 246, Folder 6)
    - Convention, 22nd: Convention Resolutions, 1979 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Convention, 22nd: District Convention Resolutions, 1979 (Box 245, Folder 7-10, Box 246, Folder 1-3)
    - Convention, 22nd: Draft Reports and Notes, 1979 (Box 50, Folder 9-10)
    - Convention, 22nd: Draft Resolution on Afro-American Liberation, 1979 (Box 246, Folder 4-5)
    - Convention, 22nd: International Night, 1979 (Box 246, Folder 6)
    - Convention, 22nd: Main Political Report, 1979 (Box 246, Folder 7-8)
    - Convention, 22nd: Main Political Resolution, 1979 (Box 246, Folder 9, Box 247, Folder 1)
    - Convention, 22nd: Notes and Correspondence, 1979 (Box 247, Folder 2)
    - Convention, 22nd: Resolutions and Greetings, 1979 (Box 239, Folder 8)
    - Convention, 23rd: Commission on Mass Agitation, Propaganda, and Party Education, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Convention, 23rd: Constitution, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Convention, 23rd: Culture and Resolutions, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 23rd: Guests, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Convention, 23rd: Decisions, Reports, Project, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Convention, 23rd: Discussion Notes and Agendas, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Convention, 23rd: Main Report, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Convention, 23rd: Pre-Convention Documents and Reports, 1983 (Box 239, Folder 9-11)
    - Convention, 23rd: Pre-Convention Discussion, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 8-9)
    - Convention, 23rd: Pre-Convention Discussion and Resolutions, 1983 (Box 51, Folder 10-12)
    - Convention, 23rd: Reports, 1983 (Box 52, Folder 1-2)
    - Convention, 23rd: Resolutions, 1983 (Box 52, Folder 3-5)
    - Convention, 23rd: Rules, Procedures, and Agenda, 1983 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Convention, 23rd: Workshops, 1983 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Convention, 24th: Afro-American Equality, 1987 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Convention, 24th: Chicano, Mexican-American Equality, 1987 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Convention, 24th: Discussion, 1987 (Box 52, Folder 10-11)
    - Convention, 24th: Discussion, 1987 (Box 53, Folder 1-2)
    - Convention, 24th: Draft Resolutions, 1987 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 24th: Draft Political Resolution (DPR), 1987 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Convention, 24th: Draft Resolutions, 1987 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Convention, 24th: General, 1987 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Convention. 24th: Notes, 1987 (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Convention, 24th: Opening Remarks, 1987 (Box 54, Folder 1-3)
    - Convention, 24th: Party Resolutions, 1987 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Convention, 24th: Pre-Convention Materials, 1987 (Box 54, Folder 5-6)
    - Convention, 24th: Proposal Rules of Order and Guidelines, 1987 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Convention, 24th: Reports on Convention Workshops, 1987 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Convention, 24th: Report and Discussion, 1987 (Box 226, Folder 1)
    - Convention, 24th: Reports and Resolutions, 1987 (Box 239, Folder 12-13)
    - Convention, 24th: Resolutions, 1987 (Box 55, Folder 1-9)
    - Convention, 24th: Resolutions, 1987 (Box 56, Folder 1-3)
    - Convention, 24th: Resolutions and Pre-Convention Discussion, 1987 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Convention, 24th: Resolutions of the Women's Movement, 1987 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - Convention, 25th: Another View, 1991 (Box 56, Folder 6-7)
    - Convention, 25th: Delegate Challenges, 1991 (Box 56, Folder 8-9)
    - Convention, 25th: Delegates, 1991 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Convention, 25th: Delegates, Stacking and National Convention Turnover, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Convention, 25th: Discussion Guidelines, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Convention, 25th: Discussion on Discussing Discussion Document Prior to Convention, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 25th: Discussion on Insensitivity in Leadership, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 4-5)
    - Convention, 25th: Discussion on Unity Prior to Convention, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 6-8)
    - Convention, 25th: Election of Leadership Discussions, 1991 (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - Convention, 25th: Election of Leadership Discussions, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Convention, 25th: Gus Hall Remarks, 1989, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Convention, 25th: Herbert Aptheker Article and Young Communist League, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 25th: Initiative Circulation, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Convention, 25th: Message Discussing Discussion Document Prior to Convention, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Convention, 25th: National Board on Factionalism, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - Convention, 25th: The National Board Prior to Convention, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - Convention, 25th: Our View, 1991 (Box 58, Folder 8)
    - Convention, 25th: Pre-Convention Panels, 1990 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Convention, 25th: Proposals and Drafts, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Convention, 25th: Resolution Drafts, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Convention, 25th: Transport, 1991 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Extraordinary Conference: Materials, 1982 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Extraordinary Conference: Workshops, 1982 (Box 59, Folder 6-7)
    - Extraordinary Conference, 2nd: Keynote, 1982 (Box 239, Folder 14)
    - Ideological Conference: Agendas and Arrangements, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 8)
    - Ideological Conference: Discussion, Miscellaneous, 1988, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 9)
    - Ideological Conference: Discussion Articles Strategy, 1989 (Box 59, Folder 10)
    - Ideological Conference: Discussion Articles Strategy, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Ideological Conference: Discussion Materials and Schedule, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 2-3)
    - Ideological Conference: Post-Conference Articles, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - Ideological Conference: Post-Conference Articles Disposed of, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Ideological Conference: Report 2, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 6)
    - Ideological Conference: Reports, 1989 (Box 239, Folder 15)
    - Ideological Conference: Strategy, 1989-1992 (Box 60, Folder 7)
    - Ideological Conference: Workshops, 1989 (Box 60, Folder 8-9)
    - National Conference on African-American Equality and the Struggle Against Racism, 1990 October (Box 239, Folder 16)
    - National Mid-Term Conference: Reports, 1986 (Box 240, Folder 1)
    - National Conference on Utilities, 1979 (Box 60, Folder 10)
    - National Conference on Utilities, 1979 (Box 61, Folder 1-3)
    - National Conference on the Working Class, 1991 June 29-30 (Box 239, Folder 17)
    - Party Conference on Work Among Youth: Opening Remarks, 1984 (Box 240, Folder 2)
    - Special Convention: Accounts, circa 1968 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - Special Convention: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Special Convention: Delegate and Alternative Card, 1968 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Special Convention: Draft Program, 1968 (Box 61, Folder 7-9)
    - Special Convention: New Party Program, 1968 (Box 61, Folder 10)
    - Special Convention: Party Building, 1968 (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Special Convention: Party Building Report, 1968 (Box 62, Folder 2-4)
  - Subseries I.D: Elections, 1930-1988; 2.5 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 record carton
    This subseries contains a small amount of documentation related to elections of Communist Party candidates. The bulk of these materials document the presidential campaigns of Gus Hall and running mate Jarvis Tyner in the 1970s. They include campaign memoranda sent to Party members, correspondence related to ballot petitioning efforts, electorate research, candidate schedules, press releases, and campaign flyers.
    Files on election campaigns are arranged chronologically by election date, and general election files are listed alphabetically by topic.
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign (Box 62, Folder 5-8)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign (Box 226, Folder 2-3)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: District and Candidate Schedules (Box 226, Folder 4-5)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Election Results Minority Candidates (Box 226, Folder 6)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Flyers (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Mass Media (Box 226, Folder 7)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Memos and Correspondence (Box 226, Folder 8)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Notes (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Petition Pacesetters (Box 226, Folder 9)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Press Releases (Box 226, Folder 10)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: State Ballot Petitioning (Box 226, Folder 11-12)
    - 1972 Hall/Tyner Campaign: State Ballots (Box 226, Folder 13-15)
    - 1976 Hall/Tyner Campaign (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - 1976 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Mandate for Struggle Pamphlet (Box 240, Folder 3)
    - 1976 Hall/Tyner Campaign: Nominating and Ballot Requirements, 1975-1976 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - 1980 Hall/Davis Campaign (Box 63, Folder 6-8)
    - 1984 Hall/Davis Campaign (Box 63, Folder 9-10)
    - 1984 Hall/Davis Campaign (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - 1984 Hall/Davis Campaign: Election Reports and Bulletins (Box 240, Folder 4)
    - 1984 General Election: Communist Party Reaction (Box 64, Folder 2)
    - 1984 General Election: Statistics on Electorate (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - 1988 General Election (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - Elections: Party History and Candidates, 1930s-1940s (Box 226, Folder 15)
    - Elections: Partisan Politics and Candidates, 1956 (Box 226, Folder 16)
    - Electoral: Communist Party Candidates, 1972-1976 (Box 226, Folder 17-18)
    - Electoral: State and National Politics, 1967-1978 (Box 226, Folder 19)
  - Subseries I.E: National Bodies, 1960-1991; 7.5 Linear Feet in 11 manuscript boxes, 1 record carton, and 2 cassette boxes; 37 audiocassettes
    This subseries contains minutes, discussion notes and transcripts, agendas, reports, and resolutions from meetings of the national administrative bodies of the Communist Party. National bodies documented in this subseries include the National Board, National Committee, Central Committee, National Council, Political Committee, and Program Committee. In several files the Central Committee and National Council meetings overlap. The Central Committee was the leading body of the Communist Party and responsible for the development of Party policy. The National Council, established in 1972, was created to assist the Central Committee with implementation of Party mobilization. The bulk of Central Committee member served on the National Council and consequently the two bodies held many meetings together. Also included in this subseries are 22 audio recordings from a 1990 Program Committee, which include discussions and reports from the meeting.
    Files in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by committee name.
    - Administrative Committee: Meeting Minutes and Notes, 1968-1972 (Box 64, Folder 5-6)
    - Central Committee: Letter to the Communist Party of the People's Republic of China, 1979 (Box 240, Folder 6)
    - Central Committee: Meeting, 1972-1981 (Box 64, Folder 7-10)
    - Central Committee: Meeting, 1981-1986 (Box 65, Folder 1-7)
    - Central Committee: Report Outline, 1984 (Box 226, Folder 20)
    - Central Committee: Reports to the Committee, 1980-1986 (Box 240, Folder 7-10)
    - Central Committee: Reviews of Hanford, 1980 (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Central Committee/National Committee, 1983 (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - Central Committee/National Committee: Clippings, undated (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Central Committee/National Committee: Discussion Notes, 1973-1978 (Box 65, Folder 11)
    - Central Committee/National Committee: Meeting, 1960-1963 (Box 65, Folder 12)
    - Central Committee/National Committee: Reports and Statements, 1970-1984 (Box 65, Folder 13)
    - Central Committee/National Council: Meeting, 1978-1980 (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
    - Central Review Commission, 1983-1984 (Box 66, Folder 3)
    - National Board: Resolutions and Statements on Factionalism, 1991 (Box 66, Folder 4-6)
    - National Committee, 1990 January 27 (Box 233, Cassette 10)
    - National Committee, 1991 January (Box 233, Cassette 11, Box Shared Tamiment 111, Cd ref12)
    - National Committee, 1991 January (Box 233, Cassette 12-13)
    - National Committee: Correspondence, 1971 (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - National Committee: Discussion, 1990 (Box 66, Folder 8)
    - National Committee: Discussion, 1991 (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - National Committee: Discussion: Transcripts, 1990 (Box 66, Folder 9-10)
    - National Committee: Discussion: Transcripts, 1990 (Box 67, Folder 1-3)
    - National Committee: Discussions, Systems and Names, 1991 (Box 67, Folder 4)
    - National Committee: Meeting, 1966-1970 (Box 67, Folder 5-8)
    - National Committee: Meeting, 1970-1971 (Box 68, Folder 1-8)
    - National Committee: Meeting, 1971-1991 (Box 69, Folder 1-8)
    - National Committee: Pre-Convention Discussion: Remarks of Carl Bloice, 1991 September 8 (Box 240, Folder 11)
    - National Committee: Reports to the Committee, 1989-1991 (Box 240, Folder 12-14)
    - National Committee: Votes and Convention, 1968-1968 (Box 226, Folder 21-22)
    - National Committee/National Council: Discussion, 1990 (Box 69, Folder 10)
    - National Committee/National Council: Meeting, 1990 (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - National Council: Biographies, undated (Box 226, Folder 23)
    - National Council: Main Political Report, 1977 May 28 (Box 240, Folder 15)
    - National Council/National Executive Board: Meeting, 1964-1965 (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - National Executive Board: Discussion, 1986 (Box 69, Folder 13)
    - Political Bureau: Special Bulletins, 1985-1987 (Box 240, Folder 16)
    - Political Bureau: "We Have to Change So We Can Grow" by Gus Hall, 1982 (Box 240, Folder 17)
    - Political Committee: Bulletins, 1973-1974 (Box 70, Folder 1-4)
    - Political Committee: Minutes, 1968-1970 (Box 70, Folder 5-9)
    - Political Committee: Minutes, 1970 (Box 71, Folder 1-3)
    - Political Committee: Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 71, Folder 4-9)
    - Political Committee: Minutes, 1971-1974 (Box 72, Folder 1-5)
    - Political Committee: Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 72, Folder 6-7)
    - Political Committee: Extras (Reports and Memoranda), 1990-1991 (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - Program Committee: Meetings, 1990-1991 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Program Committee: Meeting: Transcript, 1990 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Program Committee: Meeting: Transcript and Responses, 1990-1991 (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Program Committee: New Party Program: Drafts, 1977-1979 (Box 73, Folder 4-5)
    - Program Committee: New Party Program: Drafts and Discussions, 1980 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Program Committee: Notes, 1990-1991 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Program Committee: Originals (Reports, Memorandums, Correspondence, etc.), 1990-1991 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Program Committee: Reports and Memoranda, 1990-1991 (Box 74, Folder 2-3)
    - Program Committee: Report, 1991 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Program Committee: Topics and Commentary on New CPUSA Program, 1990 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Program Committee: Ends 2 Thirds Through Procedure, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 14)
    - Program Committee: Tape 2: Jim Jackson, Danny Rubin, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 15)
    - Program Committee: Tape I: Jim Jackson Program Committee Opening, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 16)
    - Program Committee: Tape I: Side A: Organization: Jim Jackson Strategy Side B: Jim Jackson on Strategy, Jarvis on Strategy, Mike Discussion on Strategy, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 17)
    - Program Committee:Tape II: Side A: Mike, Barry Discussion on Strategy Side B: Barry, Jim S. Discussion on Strategy, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 18, Box 238, Cassette 209)
      Includes a duplicate copy.
    - Program Committee:Tape III: Side A: Jim S., Lou Discussion on Strategy Side B: Lou Discussion on Strategy, Scottie on W.C., 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 19, Box 238, Cassette 210)
    - Program Committee: Tape IV: Side A: Scottie and Danny on W.C., Jarvis Discussion on W.C. Side B: Jarvis, Charlene Discussion on W.C., 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 20, Box 238, Cassette 211)
    - Program Committee: Tape V: Side A: Charlene Discussion on W.C. Tim J. on Afro. Side B: Tim J. on Afro. Jim S. Disc. Afro., 1991 December (Box 233, Cassette 21)
    - Program Committee:Tape V: Side A: Charlene Disc. W.C. Tim J. on Afro. Side B: Tim J. on Afro. Rick on Afro. Jim S. Disc. Afro, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 22)
    - Program Committee: Tape VI: Side A: Scottie on Afro. Lorenzo on Afro. Side B: Lorenzo Disc. Afro. Charlene on Peace, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 23, Box 238, Cassette 212)
    - Program Committee:Tape VII: Side A: Charlene on Peace Tom F. on Peace Jim J. Discussion on Peace Side B: Jim J. Peace Kendra Discussion on Peace, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 24, Box 238, Cassette 213)
    - Program Committee:Tape VIII: Side A: Kendra Discussion Peace Danny on National Oppression, Kendra Disc on N.O. Side B: Kendra Discussion National Oppression, Fern on Women, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 25, Box 238, Cassette 214)
    - Program Committee:Tape IX: Side A: Fern on Women, Danny Discussion on Women Side B: Danny Discussion on Women, Lou on Socialism, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 26, Box 238, Cassette 216)
    - Program Committee: Tape X: Side A: Lou on Socialism, Jim J. Discussion on Socio. Side B: Charlene Discussion no Socialism, Kendra Discussion on Socio., 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 27, Box Shared Tamiment 111, Cd ref21, Box 238, Cassette 215)
    - Program Committee: Tape XI: Kendra-Lou Discussion on Socialism, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 28)
    - Program Committee: Tape XI: Kendra-Socialism, Lou Discussion Socialism, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 29)
    - Program Committee: Tape XII: Side A: Democracy-Jim S., Barry Side B: Jim J. Discussion on Democracy, Ends with Charlene Discussion on Democracy, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 30, Box 238, Cassette 217)
    - Program Committee: Tape XIII: Side A: Charlene Discussion on Demo. Side B: Ends Kendra on Party, Barry Starts Discussion, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 31, Box 238, Cassette 218)
    - Program Committee: Tape XIV: Side A: Barry and Lou Discussion on the Party Side B: Jim S. Discussion on the Party, Kendra Conclusion on the Party, Procedure, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 32, Box 238, Cassette 219)
    - Program Committee: Tape XV: Side A: Procedure Ends 2/3 Through Tape, 1990 December (Box 233, Cassette 33)
    - Program Committee: Tape 1: Organization: Jim Jackson on Strategy, 1990 December (Box 238, Cassette 206)
    - Program Committee: Tape 3: Kendra, 1990 December (Box 238, Cassette 207)
- Series II: Youth Commission and Youth Organizations, 1924-1990; 12 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes, 3 record cartons, and 1 cassette box; 2 audiocassettes
  This series contains flyers, correspondence, agendas, pamphlets, publications, as well as Rubin's notes and drafts, which document his work with the Communist Party's Youth Commission and affiliated youth organizations, including the W.E.B. DuBois Clubs, Labor Youth League, Progressive Youth Organizing Committee, Young Communist League, and Young Workers Liberation League, dated 1940s-1980s. Files related to Rubin's work with youth organizations, notably his work at Swarthmore College and involvement in the American Youth for Democracy (AYD) and Labor Youth League (LYL) predate his membership in the Communist Party. While the AYD and LYL were Communist Party affiliated organizations, Rubin's files on these organizations specifically relate to youth organizing in the Philadelphia area. The bulk of the series document Rubin's work as National Youth Secretary, but also include Youth Commission materials dated after Rubin's work as Youth Secretary. These materials include reports, meeting minutes, outlines, educational guides, and publications related to the Youth Commission and affiliated organization, the Young Communist League and Young Workers Liberation League dated as late as 1990.
  Files in this series are arranged alphabetically by organization name and topic.
  Biographical / Historical
  Daniel Rubin was raised in a communist household and was involved in progressive and communist activism from an early age. In 1947, he joined the Progressive Citizens of America and became a member of the Young Progressives of America. Around the same time, Rubin also joined the Philadelphia-based organization the Citizens for a Free City College, becoming the chair of the Youth Division and joined the Communist Party-affiliated American Youth for Democracy (AYD). As a student at Swarthmore College between 1949 and 1951, Rubin participated in Young Progressive for America political campaigns against McCarthyism, Cold War foreign policy, and segregation. He began law school at University of Pennsylvania in 1953 where he became a founding member of the Eastern Pennsylvania Labor Youth League (LYL). Between 1955 and 1960 Rubin began organizing for the Communist Party's Youth Club in Philadelphia, and served as a delegate to the 16th Convention of the Communist Party in 1956. He became the Party's National Youth Secretary in 1960, a position he held until the end of 1964.
  - American Youth for Democracy Publication: Youth, 1945-1947 (Box 74, Folder 6)
  - Communist Party: Public Role and Youth, 1958-1960, 1969 (Box 74, Folder 7)
  - Communist Party: Report on Youth, 1966 (Box 74, Folder 8)
  - Communist Viewpoint, 1961-1963 (Box 74, Folder 9)
  - Curriculum Vitae (Old), 1962 (Box 74, Folder 10)
  - Defense: McCarran Act, 1961-1962 (Box 226, Folder 24)
  - Draft Youth Report, 1966 (Box 226, Folder 25)
  - Du Bois Clubs, 1968 (Box 75, Folder 1-3)
  - Du Bois Clubs of America: Publications, 1964-1968 (Box 75, Folder 4)
  - Du Bois Clubs of America: Publications: Insurgent, circa 1967 (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Du Bois Clubs of America, 1965 (Box 75, Folder 6)
  - Encampment and Youth Question Materials, 1966 (Box 226, Folder 26)
  - Free City College Campaign: Philadelphia, 1948 (Box 75, Folder 7)
  - High School/Vocational School Students Statistics, undated (Box 75, Folder 8)
  - Independence Day (July 4th) Coalition, 1976 (Box 75, Folder 9)
  - International Relations: University Clubs, 1960-1961 (Box 226, Folder 27)
  - International Situation and Military Spending, 1982 (Box 75, Folder 10)
  - International Youth, circa 1962 (Box 75, Folder 11-12)
  - Labor Youth League (LYL), 1949-1956 (Box 76, Folder 1-4)
  - Labor Youth League (LYL), circa 1950s (Box 226, Folder 28)